<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Website on Gazoo.vrv</title>
    <link>https://donw.io/tags/website/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Website on Gazoo.vrv</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 19:35:05 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://donw.io/tags/website/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The History of a Future Platform, Part 2: Stunt Island</title>
      <link>https://donw.io/post/future-platform-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 19:35:05 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://donw.io/post/future-platform-2/</guid>
      <description>Part 1: Why
Part 2: Stunt Island 

I&#39;m a late 80s to late 90s gamer: some of my most imprinted memories come from that period. I remember vividly two incredible WOW! moments that changed my life. The first was seeing the DOOM screen melt on one of my dad&#39;s school&#39;s library machines:

  With a Master System at home as my only point of reference, DOOM was so many worlds apart</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The History of a Future Platform, Part 1: Why</title>
      <link>https://donw.io/post/future-platform-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 08:18:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://donw.io/post/future-platform-1/</guid>
      <description>My attempt to rethink the way games are made 

In 2012, after shipping Fable 3 on Xbox 360 and PC, supporting some DLCs, creating Fable Heroes with some funky new rendering research and helping the team understand the workflows and transition to Unreal Engine 3.... (phew)... I was completely worn down and demoralised. As a team we did some amazing things. I made some life-long friends and was immensely satisfied with the journey we&#39;d taken (no, not that one).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Host, Server and Site Generator</title>
      <link>https://donw.io/post/a-new-host-server-site/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2016 21:48:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://donw.io/post/a-new-host-server-site/</guid>
      <description>And we are back! It must be a year now since my old site donw.org went dark for many reasons, including being busy working on my own game. There&#39;s some big changes with this new setup:
 I own the domain donw.io this time round. I&#39;ve gone through a bunch of domains -- donw.org, donw.co.uk, etc. -- that I used to pay somebody else to manage for me. That was obviously not the right way of going about this as I no longer own them.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>